Guide to the New England Society of American Foresters Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
New England Society of American Foresters records
1920-1999
MS 1656
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
The records include minutes of meetings, committee files, correspondence, membership lists, and programs for meetings, which relate to the administration and work of the New England Society of American Foresters. The records include minutes and other materials dating from the organization of the society as the New England Section of the Society of American Foresters.
New England Society of American Foresters
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were transferred from the Yale Forestry Library in 1991 and were the gift of the New England Society of American Foresters in 1994 and 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Scope and Contents
The records of the New England Society of American Foresters include minutes of meetings, committee files, correspondence, membership lists, programs for annual meetings, and other materials relating to the administration and work of the society prior to 1980, when the society changed its name. The records are arranged in chronological order.
For the years 1920 to 1951 the files include two bound volumes of minutes for annual and executive committee meetings, committee reports, and meeting programs. A small number of files containing similar but unbound material for the period 1940 to 1964 follow.
The bulk of the section's records, however, date from 1965 to 1977. Files for the years are again unbound. There are yearly "General files," which contain meeting programs, minutes, membership lists, budgets, financial statements, committee reports, correspondence, and press releases. There are also files on particular topics of interest, such as pending legislation and forest policy activities. The period 1972 to 1975 is particularly well documented through the copies of outgoing letters by Walter R. Gooley, Jr., who served as secretary-treasurer, vice-chairman, and then chairman of the section.
At the end of the files there are two folders of records from the Granite State Chapter and several folders of material relating to the Society of American Foresters, particularly the House of Section Delegates' meetings and the business of various committees. The latter are arranged alphabetically.
The records of the section were transferred from the Yale Forestry Library in 1991. The section's executive committee formally donated the records to the Yale University Library in 1994. The society's newsletter, the "New England Section-Society of American Foresters News Quarterly," is available at the Yale Forestry Library.
Biographical / Historical
The New England Society of American Foresters was founded as the New England Section of the Society of American Foresters in 1920. The Society of American Foresters had been organized in 1903 "to further the cause of forestry in America by fostering a spirit of comradeship among foresters; by creating opportunities for a free exchange of views upon forestry and allied subjects; and by disseminating a knowledge of the purpose and achievements of forestry." The Society authorized the establishment of sections wherever there were enough active members to form a strong local organization.
The New England Section was organized in the office of Massachusetts State Forester Harold O. Cook. At that first meeting in Boston, fourteen foresters were present, and Professor James W. Toumey of Yale University was elected the first chairman and H. O. Cook was elected secretary. Initially the section allowed for members from the six New England states, but the membership base was eventually broadened to include members from the eastern Canadian provinces.
The purposes of the society are fostered by the section through its meetings and, since 1940, through the publication of a quarterly news bulletin. The semiannual section meetings (the winter annual meeting and the summer annual meeting) provide time for the conducting of section business as well as the presentation of papers, debate over policy, and social interaction. The section has been concerned with many problems of silviculture and management, primarily the problems of reproduction and increased growth. Depression and employment in the lumbering industry, storm and flood damage, and salvage operations, taxation, recreation, wildlife, and federal land acquisition have been other subjects addressed by the section.
The Society of American Foresters also authorized the creation of chapters within the sections. Within the New England Section there are three chapters: the Granite State Chapter, the Green Mountain Chapter, and the Yankee Chapter, which is composed of members from Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island. The New England Section of the Society of American Foresters changed its name to the New England Society of American Foresters in 1980.
The section's Forest History Committee produced a history of the section in 1965. For further information, consultHistory of the New England Section, Society of American Foresters(Box 2, folder 11).
Foresters -- United States; Forests and forestry; New England; New England Society of American Foresters; Society of American Foresters. New England Section
- Inventory
  - Section records
    - Meetings, 1st-12th [minutes and records], 1920-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meeting programs, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meetings, 13th- 32nd[minutes and records], 1932-1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - General files, 1940-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4 - 6)
    - General files, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7 - 10)
    - History of the New England Section, Society of American Foresters, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - General files, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Rules for distinguished service awards, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General files, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Eastern Wilderness Act of 1974, 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General files, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 16 - 18)
    - Forest policy activities [national and section positions], 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - General files, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "A Half Century of Forestry", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - General files, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Winter meeting papers, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Business meetings and Executive Committee meetings [minutes], 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hotel arrangements, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Legislation and Policy Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Public Affairs, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - General files, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Committee on Forest Wild Lands in the East, [ca. 1972] (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Gooley, Walter R., Jr. [correspondence], 1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Department of the Interior hearings on nationwide recreation planning, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Summer meeting, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Land Use Planning Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - News Quarterly, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Resolutions, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Special Panel on Professional Preparation, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Executive Committee [minutes of meetings, correspondence], 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Northeastern Forest Pest Council, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Membership lists, 1972-1978, n. d. (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - General files, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Annual meetings, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 41 - 42)
    - Committee reports, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Gooley, Walter R., Jr. [correspondence], 1973 (Box 4, Folder 44 - 45)
    - Management-Silviculture-Protection Committee, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Winter meeting [publicity], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Nominating Committee, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Secretary-Treasurer, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - General files, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Gooley, Walter R., Jr. [correspondence], 1974 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - General files, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Gooley, Walter R., Jr. [correspondence], 1975 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - General files, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - State of Maine citation [certificate], 1978 March 9 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Unidentified, n. d. (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Granite State Chapter records, 1961-1962, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 57 - 58)
  - Society of American Foresters
    - Committee for Standard Section Bylaws, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Committees, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1966, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 61 - 63)
    - Council meetings, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Forest policy position statements, 1973-1976 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Gifford Pinchot Building Committee, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - House of Delegates meeting, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 67 - 70)
    - The SAF Manual, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - New Hampshire news segment on section meeting, 1977 March 18; 1 (Box 7)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-018
  Scope and Contents
  Through correspondence, minutes of meetings, and membership and financial records, the bulk of the material in this accession documents the work of the New England Society of American Foresters during the 1980s and the early 1990s. The materials in the first two boxes are arranged in rough chronological order. The remaining box contains materials organized by topic.
  - Winter meeting proceedings, 1953 (Box 1)
  - News Quarterly, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Financial account book, 1962-1981 (Box 1)
  - Membership directory, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee reports, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Winter meeting, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Forest Practices Study Committee report, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Winter meeting arrangements, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee and business meeting minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Meeting records, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Meeting records, 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Meeting records, elections, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Meeting records, elections, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Meeting records, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Expenditures, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Membership lists, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee and annual meeting records, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Directories, membership, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee and annual meeting records, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Directories, membership, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee and annual meeting records, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Directories, membership [papers of Ted Howard, chair], 1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee and annual meeting records, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1986-1988, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
  - Winter meeting program and business meeting, 1986-1998 (Box 2)
  - Accreditation, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Addresses, officials, 1982-1986 (Box 3)
  - Awards, national, 1987, n. d. (Box 3)
  - Bethesda correspondence, 1988-1998 (Box 3)
  - Bylaws, 1966-1997 (Box 3)
  - Calendar, action, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Certification programs, 1984-1995 (Box 3)
  - Communications workshop, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Congress, forest, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Connecticut chapter, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Continuing forestry education, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Council nominations, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Cultural diversity, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Deaths, 1986-1998 (Box 3)
  - Distinguished Service Award, 1964-1977 (Box 3)
  - Divisions, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Editor, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Education Committee, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Election, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Ethics Committee, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Executive director, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Fellows nominations, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Financial reports, 1985-1988 (Box 3)
  - Foresters' Fund, 1992-1998 (Box 3)
  - Grants, 1985-1998 (Box 3)
  - "Great American Woodlots", 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Habitat, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Health-Productivity report, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - History, revision, 1965-1994 (Box 3)
  - IRS tax exemption, 1971, 1990-1995 (Box 3)
  - Mission Statement Committee, 1990-1995 (Box 3)
  - Natural Areas Committee, 1973-1979 (Box 3)
  - New York Society of American Foresters, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - News Quarterly, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Northern Forest Alliance, 1993-1997 (Box 3)
  - Northern Forest Land Council, 1988-1994 (Box 3)
  - Position statements, 1982-1997 (Box 3)
  - Progression to two year terms, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Public lands management legislation, proposed, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Resolutions, 1972-1987 (Box 3)
  - Society of American Foresters (Box 3)
    - Council meetings, 1983-1986 (Box 3)
    - Dues, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Internal Affairs Committee, [ca. 1983?] (Box 3)
    - Renewable Natural Resources Foundation dispute, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Student chapter activities and affairs, 1973-1979, 1984 (Box 3)
  - United States Congress, 1976, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Vendor lists, winter meeting, 1979-1980, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
  - Women in forestry, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
  - Working groups, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
  - Loose material [to be sorted], 1968-1978 (Box 3)